Guide to the Robert K. Merton Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series VII: Writings, 1931-2002
  - Subseries VII.3: Books By, 1933-2002
    - On the Shoulders of Giants: A Shandean Postscript
      - Forms of Publication, 1990 (Box 501, Folder 11)
      - German Translation, 1979-1980, (2 Folders) (Box 501, Folder 12 to 13)
      - Gould, Stephen, 1992 (Box 501, Folder 14)
      - Hebrew "Tradition," 1975-2002 (Box 502, Folder 1)
      - Heine, Heinrich, 1991 (Box 502, Folder 2)
      - Hivnor, Maggie
        - General, 1992, undated (Box 502, Folder 3)
        - Book Party, 1993 (Box 502, Folder 4)
        - Correspondence, 1980-1993 (Box 502, Folder 5)
      - Illustrations and Figures, 1965, 1973 (Box 502, Folder 6)
      - Imagery not in Book, 1964-1978 (Box 502, Folder 7)
      - In Praise of, 1965-1983 (Box 502, Folder 8)
      - Inscriptions, 1971-1989 (Box 502, Folder 9)
      - Italian Translation
        - General, 1981, 1992 (Box 502, Folder 10)
        - Gift Copies, 1991-1993 (Box 502, Folder 11)
        - Movia, Giovanna, 1989-1992 (Box 502, Folder 12)
      - Jeauneau, Edouard--Articles, undated, (2 Folders) (Box 502, Folder 13 to 14)
      - John of Salisbury, undated (Box 503, Folder 1)
      - Jovanovich, Peter, 1965-1991 (Box 503, Folder 2)
      - Jovanovich, William, 1980-1991 (Box 503, Folder 3)
      - Klibanksy, Raymond, 1992 (Box 503, Folder 4)
      - Levin, Harry--On Solecisms, 1965, 1985-1986 (Box 503, Folder 5)
      - Little Men and Women, 1985 (Box 503, Folder 6)
      - Lucan, M. Annaei, undated (Box 503, Folder 7)
      - Making of the Book
        - General, 1964-1967, 1983 (Box 503, Folder 8)
        - Early Notes, Used and Unused in Print, 1958-1967 (Box 503, Folder 9)
      - Multiple Appearances in Newton, 1986-1988 (Box 503, Folder 10)
      - New York Times Error, 1989 (Box 503, Folder 11)
      - Newton, Isaac, undated (Box 503, Folder 12)
      - On the Paperback Cover, 1992 (Box 503, Folder 13)
      - On the Serious Side, 1966-1984 (Box 503, Folder 14)
      - Onomasticon or a Sort of Index, undated (Box 503, Folder 15)
      - Origins--Original Letter to Bernard Bailyn, 1959-1961, (3 Folders) (Box 504, Folder 1 to 3)
      - Other Books and Articles with Similar Title, 1977-1991, (2 Folders) (Box 504, Folder 4 to 5)
      - "Otsogian" Figures, 1966, 1977-1989 (Box 504, Folder 6)
      - Paperback Sales, 1989-1991 (Box 504, Folder 7)
      - Parodies of the Shandean Tone, 1988 (Box 504, Folder 8)
      - Permissions for Extracts, 1964-1965 (Box 504, Folder 9)
      - Poole, Reginald Lane and Waddell, Helen, 1966 (Box 504, Folder 10)
      - Post-ltalianate Edition
        - Edits of Foreward and Postface--Kiser, Jo Ann, 1992 (Box 504, Folder 11)
        - Materials for, 1975-1984 (Box 504, Folder 12)
        - Publicity, 1991-1993 (Box 504, Folder 13)
        - Reviews, 1994-1997 (Box 504, Folder 14)
        - Sales, 1993 (Box 504, Folder 15)
        - Translation of Umberto Eco's Introduction, 1992-1993 (Box 504, Folder 16)
      - Postface
        - General, 1987-1993 (Box 505, Folder 1)
        - Comments, 1992 (Box 505, Folder 2)
        - Final Notes, 1965-1976 (Box 505, Folder 3)
        - Footnotes, undated (Box 505, Folder 4)
        - Outlines, 1992 (Box 505, Folder 5)
        - Rejects, 1982-1988 (Box 505, Folder 6)
        - Used Items, 1988-1992 (Box 505, Folder 7)
      - Pouissin, Nicolas, 1993 (Box 505, Folder 8)
      - Presidential Talk--Bowen, William, 1985-1997 (Box 505, Folder 9)
      - Priscian's Dictum, undated (Box 505, Folder 10)
      - Production, 1985 (Box 505, Folder 11)
      - Publisher's Interest, 1989-1991 (Box 505, Folder 12)
      - The Purloined Letter, 1992 (Box 505, Folder 13)
      - Reprinting, 1991-1993 (Box 505, Folder 14)
      - Requests, 1966-1981 (Box 505, Folder 15)
      - Reviews
        - General, 1965-1976 (Box 505, Folder 16)
        - Italian and Spanish, 1997 (Box 505, Folder 17)
        - Oster, Malcolm, 1994 (Box 505, Folder 18)
      - Selected Comments, 1965-1984 (Box 506, Folder 1)
      - Serendipity Poems, 1987, undated (Box 506, Folder 2)
      - Sinkler, Rebecca, 1991-1992 (Box 506, Folder 3)
      - Sources of Aphorism, 1992 (Box 506, Folder 4)
      - Spanish Edition, 1989-1990 (Box 506, Folder 5)
      - Ulysses, 1965 (Box 506, Folder 6)
      - University of Chicago Press, 1993 (Box 506, Folder 7)
      - Usages not Recorded in 1965-1967 Prints, 1966-1984 (Box 506, Folder 8)
      - Use in President Reagan's State of the Union Address, 1977-1987 (Box 506, Folder 9)
      - Variants and Public Displays of Truncated Aphorism, 1968-1982 (Box 506, Folder 10)
      - Vicennial Edition
        - Decter, Jacqueline, 1978-1986 (Box 506, Folder 11)
        - Gift Copies, 1985 (Box 506, Folder 12)
        - Reviews, 1986-1987 (Box 506, Folder 13)
      - A Word-of-Mouth Book, 1969-1992 (Box 506, Folder 14)
  - Subseries VII.4: Edits for Others, 1942-1999
    Merton proclaimed he possessed "a lifelong addiction to editing." This sentiment is reflected in the considerable amount of editorial material comprising Subseries VII.4. The subseries includes draft copies of a wide variety of works, along with Merton's extensive edits and comments. In some cases, Merton drafted separate documents to comment on manuscripts and essays of others, which are present here. The series also contains correspondence and editing requests. Records are arranged alphabetically by author's last name or occasionally by title of work. Merton also compiled records topically, which are filed alphabetically throughout.
    - General, 1971-1991, (3 Folders) (Box 238, Folder 1-3)
    - Alba, Richard, 1984 (Box 238, Folder 4)
    - Aya, Rod, 1981-1982 (Box 238, Folder 5)
    - Baldassare, Mark, 1979 (Box 238, Folder 6)
    - Becker, Gary, 1975-1984 (Box 238, Folder 7)
    - Benson, Lee, 1987 (Box 238, Folder 8)
    - Beveridge, Andrew, undated (Box 238, Folder 9)
    - Boudon, Raymond, 1979-1983 (Box 238, Folder 10)
    - Bourgois, Philippe, 1993-1994 (Box 238, Folder 11)
    - Brubaker, Rogers, 1984 (Box 238, Folder 12)
    - C--General, 1990-1997 (Box 238, Folder 13)
    - Campbell, Don, 1966 (Box 238, Folder 14)
    - Caplow, H., 1957 (Box 238, Folder 15)
    - Cavanaugh, Michael, 1988-1996 (Box 238, Folder 16)
    - Cline, Hugh, 1976-1979 (Box 238, Folder 17)
    - Cohen, I. Bernard, 1984 (Box 349, Folder 12)
    - Cole, Jonathan
      - Sole Author, 1973-1985, undated (Box 239, Folder 1)
      - Sole Author, 1973-1985, undated (Box 240, Folder 1)
      - With Cole, Stephen, 1966-1967 (Box 240, Folder 2)
      - With Dietrich, 1975, undated (Box 240, Folder 3)
      - With Kingston, Paul, 1980 (Box 240, Folder 4)
    - Cole, Stephen
      - Sole Author, 1990-1997, (4 Folders) (Box 240, Folder 5-8)
      - With Meyer, Garry, 1984 (Box 240, Folder 9)
    - Continuities in Structural Inquiry, 1979-1980 (Box 240, Folder 10)
    - Coser, Lewis, undated
      - Et al.--Introduction to Sociology, 2nd edition, 1985, (4 Folders) (Box 241, Folder 1-4)
      - Sole Author, undated (Box 241, Folder 5)
    - Coser, Rose, 1966 (Box 241, Folder 6)
    - Cournand, Andre and Levy, Maurice, 1971 (Box 241, Folder 7)
    - Cozzens, Susan, 1980-1984 (Box 241, Folder 8)
    - Darnton, Robert, 1973 (Box 241, Folder 9)
    - Davis, Bernard, 1974 (Box 241, Folder 10)
    - Davis, Devra 1971 (Box 241, Folder 11)
    - Dedijer, Steven, 1970 (Box 241, Folder 12)
    - Denisoff, Serge, 1970-1971 (Box 241, Folder 13)
    - Dissertations--General, 1943-1970 (Box 241, Folder 14)
    - Dissertations--General, 1943-1970 (Box 242, Folder 1)
    - Ditz, Gerhard W., 1988 (Box 242, Folder 2)
    - Douglas, Mary, 1981 (Box 242, Folder 3)
    - Dulchin, Joan, 1963 (Box 242, Folder 4)
    - Elkhana, Yehuda, 1979 (Box 242, Folder 5)
    - Ellul, Jacques, 1960-1976 (Box 349, Folder 13)
    - Epstein, Cynthia, 1967, 1983-1987, (2 Folders) (Box 242, Folder 6-7)
    - Erikson, Erik, 1973, undated, (2 Folders) (Box 242, Folder 8-9)
    - Erikson, Kai, 1970 (Box 242, Folder 10)
    - Etzkowitz, Henry, 1977 (Box 242, Folder 11)
    - Fein, Helen, 1986 (Box 242, Folder 12)
    - Fischer, Claude, 1973-1975 (Box 242, Folder 13)
    - Gardner, Howard, 1996 (Box 242, Folder 14)
    - Garfield, Eugene, 1971-1992 (Box 239, Folder 2)
    - Garfield, Eugene, 1983-1992, (3 Folders) (Box 243, Folder 1-3)
    - Gieryn, Thomas, 1978 (Box 243, Folder 4)
    - Giffard, Bernard, 1977 (Box 243, Folder 5)
    - Goldblatt, Harold, 1973 (Box 243, Folder 6)
    - Haritos, Rosa, 1985 (Box 243, Folder 7)
    - Haveman, Robert, 1992 (Box 243, Folder 8)
    - Hechter, Michael, 1987-1997 (Box 243, Folder 9)
    - Hill, Robert, 1986 (Box 243, Folder 10)
    - Hudson, Barclay, 1973 (Box 243, Folder 11)
    - Hunt, Morton, 1994-1998, (3 Folders) (Box 243, Folder 12-14)
    - Janis, Irving, 1974 (Box 243, Folder 15)
    - Johnson, Allan, 1983-1987, (4 Folders) (Box 244, Folder 1-4)
    - Johnston, Barry, 1986 (Box 244, Folder 5)
    - Jones, Robert Alun, 1975 (Box 244, Folder 6)
    - Kahneman, Daniel, 1990-1991 (Box 244, Folder 7)
    - Kardiner, Abram, 1943 (Box 244, Folder 8)
    - Katz, Sue Bernard, undated (Box 244, Folder 9)
    - Kelly, Patricia Fernandez, 1993-1995 (Box 244, Folder 10)
    - Kennedy, Randall, 1986-1989, (2 Folders) (Box 244, Folder 11-12)
    - King, Chris, 1986 (Box 244, Folder 13)
    - Komarovsky, Mirra, 1949-1955, 1977 (Box 244, Folder 14)
    - Kranton, Rachel, 1998 (Box 245, Folder 1)
    - Lamont, Michele, 1996 (Box 245, Folder 2)
    - Lederberg, Joshua, 1986, undated (Box 245, Folder 3)
    - Lehrer, K., undated (Box 245, Folder 4)
    - Lennon, Mary Clare, 1989-1993 (Box 245, Folder 5)
    - Levine, Donald, 1969 (Box 245, Folder 6)
    - Levinson, Bernard, 1957-1958 (Box 245, Folder 7)
    - Lin, Nan, undated (Box 245, Folder 8)
    - Lindblom, Edward, 1974 (Box 245, Folder 9)
    - Logan, John, 1997-1998 (Box 245, Folder 10)
    - Lynd, Helen, 1957 (Box 245, Folder 11)
    - Manuscripts--General, 1975-1978 (Box 245, Folder 12)
    - Mayer, John and Rosenblatt, Aaron, 1975 (Box 245, Folder 13)
    - McAulay, Robert, 1977 (Box 245, Folder 14)
    - Mendes, Richard, 1981, (2 Folders) (Box 245, Folder 15-16)
    - Merton, Robert C., 1977-1986 (Box 246, Folder 1)
    - Messari, Peter, 1984-1986 (Box 246, Folder 2)
    - Meyer, Marshall W., 1994, (2 Folders) (Box 246, Folder 3-4)
    - Miller, S.M., 1976 (Box 246, Folder 5)
    - Mosteller, Frederick and Kruskal, William, 1978 (Box 246, Folder 6)
    - Mukerji, Chandra, 1978 (Box 246, Folder 7)
    - Myers, Samuel L., Jr., 1984 (Box 246, Folder 8)
    - Nee, Victor, 1993-1998, (3 Folders) (Box 246, Folder 9-11)
    - Needham, Elizabeth, 1999 (Box 239, Folder 3)
    - Newman, Katherine, 1995-1999 (Box 246, Folder 12)
    - Oberschall, Anthony, undated (Box 246, Folder 13)
    - Offer, Daniel, 1974 (Box 246, Folder 14)
    - O'Gorman, Hubert and Garry, Stephen, 1975 (Box 247, Folder 1)
    - Opp, Karl-Dieter, undated (Box 247, Folder 2)
    - Park, Kyeyoung, 1998 (Box 247, Folder 3)
    - Parson, Talcott--"Social Science: A Basic National Resource," 1948, (3 Folders) (Box 148, Folder 3-5)
    - Patel, Pravin, undated (Box 247, Folder 4)
    - Perez, Lisandro, 1997-1998 (Box 247, Folder 5)
    - Peterson, Richard, 1974 (Box 247, Folder 6)
    - Piel, Gerard, 1969 (Box 247, Folder 7)
    - Portes, Alejandro, 1999 (Box 247, Folder 8)
    - Price, Derek deSolla, 1983-1985 (Box 239, Folder 4)
    - Reitz, Jeff, 1968-1971 (Box 247, Folder 9)
    - Reports for Publishers, 1942-1967 (Box 247, Folder 10)
    - Requests for Edits, 1955-1960 (Box 247, Folder 11)
    - Riley, Matilda White, 1969-1986 (Box 247, Folder 12)
    - Robinson, Marshall, 1979-1985 (Box 247, Folder 13)
    - Rosen, Harvey, 1996-1997 (Box 247, Folder 14)
    - Rosenblatt, Aaron, 1987 (Box 247, Folder 15)
    - Rossi, Peter
      - Sole Author, 1984 (Box 248, Folder 1)
      - With Berk, Richard, 1984 (Box 248, Folder 2)
    - Rumbaut, Ruben, 1997-1998 (Box 248, Folder 3)
    - Russell Sage Foundation, 1981-1995, (4 Folders) (Box 248, Folder 4-7)
    - Samuelson, Paul, 1975 (Box 248, Folder 8)
    - Scholz, John, undated (Box 248, Folder 9)
    - Schott, Thomas, 1984 (Box 248, Folder 10)
    - Schutte, Jerald, 1976 (Box 248, Folder 11)
    - Selvin, Hanan, 1988 (Box 248, Folder 12)
    - Shafer, Byron, 1978-1979 (Box 248, Folder 13)
    - Shweder, Richard, 1991-1993 (Box 248, Folder 14)
    - Smelser, Neil and Swedberg, Richard, 1991 (Box 249, Folder 1)
    - Smith, R.S., 1994-1995 (Box 239, Folder 5)
    - Snizek, William, 1981-1982 (Box 249, Folder 2)
    - Stafford, Rebecca, 1976-1977, (4 Folders) (Box 249, Folder 3-6)
    - Steffan, Patricia, 1985, (2 Folders) (Box 249, Folder 7-8)
    - Stehr, Nico and Meja, Volker, 1987-1988 (Box 239, Folder 6)
    - Stern, Fritz, 1989 (Box 249, Folder 9)
    - Stewart, Donald Dean, undated, (2 Folders) (Box 148, Folder 6-7)
    - Stone, John, 1973 (Box 249, Folder 10)
    - Storer, Norman, 1963 (Box 249, Folder 11)
    - Swedberg, Richard, 1990-1998 (Box 249, Folder 12)
    - Telles, Joel Leon, 1974-1982 (Box 249, Folder 13)
    - Thackery, Arnold, 1974 (Box 250, Folder 1)
    - Thomas, Judith, 1980-1982 (Box 250, Folder 2)
    - Thompson, J. Phillip, 1996 (Box 250, Folder 3)
    - Tiryakian, Edward, 1986 (Box 250, Folder 4)
    - Toward a Metric of Science, 1977-1978 (Box 250, Folder 5)
    - Tufte, Edward, R., 1974 (Box 250, Folder 6)
    - Wacquant, Loic, 1988-1999, (3 Folders) (Box 250, Folder 7-9)
    - Wade, Robert, 1997-1998 (Box 250, Folder 10)
    - Weiner, Charles, 1968 (Box 250, Folder 11)
    - Wendt, James, 1977-1978 (Box 250, Folder 12)
    - Wilderesky, Aaron, undated (Box 250, Folder 13)
    - Zeisel, Hans, undated (Box 250, Folder 14)
    - Zeitlin, Maurice, undated (Box 250, Folder 15)
    - Zhan, Min, 1995 (Box 250, Folder 16)
    - Acknowledgements, 1947, 1963-1993 (Box 432, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1943-1993, (2 Folders) (Box 432, Folder 2 to 3)
    - DeLeon, Peter, 1992 (Box 432, Folder 4)
    - Editor's Checklist, 1953, 1975, undated (Box 432, Folder 5)
    - Editor's Notes
      - General, 1975-1988, (2 Folders) (Box 432, Folder 6 to 7)
      - On Singular Uses of Plurality, 1970-1986 (Box 432, Folder 8)
    - Editorial Rules of Thumb, 1985-1988 (Box 432, Folder 9)
    - Eugene Garfield on Merton as Editor, 1983 (Box 432, Folder 10)
    - Freight Train Modifiers: An Editor's Theme, 1987 (Box 432, Folder 11)
    - Journal Editorships, 1947-1987 (Box 432, Folder 12)
    - Larsen, Russell D., 1990 (Box 432, Folder 13)
    - On Dating First Editions, 1984-1988 (Box 433, Folder 1)
    - On Editing, 1975-1988 (Box 433, Folder 2)
    - On Severe Editing, 1985 (Box 433, Folder 3)
    - Russell Sage Foundation--Acknowledgements of Editing, 1990-1993 (Box 433, Folder 4)
    - Garfield, Eugene, 1985-1992 (Box 506, Folder 15)
  - Subseries VII.5: Translations, Compilations, Introductions and Forwards, 1959-1999
    Merton's collaboration with authors from a wide variety of fields is documented in this subseries. Projects include forwards and introductions for various books, translations of material, and editorial work. Items include correspondence, notes, drafts, and research files. This subseries is organized chronologically beginning with translations and compilations and then forwards and introductions. Information about these works may also be found in Series II.
    - History, Philosophy and Sociology of Science: Classics, Staples, and Precursors in Sociology--Compiler and Editor, with Yehuda Elkana; Arnold Thackray; Harriet Zuckerman, 1973-1980 (Box 331, Folder 8)
    - Genesis and Development of a Scientific Fact by Ludwik Fleck --From the German
      - General, 1975-1980 (Box 331, Folder 9)
      - General, 1976-1989, (3 Folders) (Box 332, Folder 1-3)
      - Colloquium, 1980-1981 (Box 332, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence
        - General, 1974-1989, (2 Folders) (Box 332, Folder 5-6)
        - Baldamus, W., 1973-1980, (2 Folders) (Box 332, Folder 7-8)
        - Kuhn, Thomas, 1976 (Box 332, Folder 9)
        - Lowy, Ilana, 1988 (Box 332, Folder 10)
        - Trenn, Thaddeus, 1975-1978 (Box 332, Folder 11)
      - Proofs, circa 1976 (Box 332, Folder 12)
      - Proofs, 1976-1977 (Box 333, Folder 1)
      - Research and Correspondence, 1964-1996 (Box 333, Folder 2)
      - Reviews, 1979-1981 (Box 333, Folder 3)
    - "The Ambivalences of Le Bon'sThe Crowd"--Introduction to the Compass Edition of Gustave Le Bon, The Crowd, 1959 (Box 333, Folder 4)
    - Social Organization Under Stress by Allen Barton, 1967, (2 Folders) (Box 333, Folder 5-6)
    - Knaurs Buch der Modernen Soziologie by Imogen Seger, 1969-1977 (Box 333, Folder 7)
    - The Structure of Society by Julian Marias, 1962-1984 (Box 333, Folder 8)
    - Training in Ambiguity: Learning Through Doing in a Mental Hospital by Rose Coser, undated (Box 333, Folder 9)
    - Little Science, Big Science....And Beyond by Derek J. de Solla Price / Eugene Garfield
      - General, 1983-1986 (Box 333, Folder 10)
      - Research, 1963-1985 (Box 333, Folder 11)
    - Comparative Anomie Research: Hidden Barriers - Hidden Potential for Social Development, Edited by Peter Atteslander; Bettina Gransow; John Western, 1999 (Box 333, Folder 12)
    - Mastering Medicine by Robert Coombs (Declined), 1976-1977 (Box 333, Folder 13)
    - Genesis and Development of a Scientific Fact by Ludwik Fleck--Proofs, undated (Box 433, Folder 5)